Guide to the Brand Blanshard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Teaching Files, 1921-1962; Series III; 2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  - Course notes
    - Contemporary Philosophy (University of Michigan), 1922 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Ethics (Wheelwright text), [ca. 1945-1961] (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Ethics (Sharp text), [ca. 1945-1961 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - General Logic (Yale University), Circa 1945-1961 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - History of Modern Philosophy seminar (Swarthmore College), Circa 1925-1945 (Box 52, Folder 8-9)
    - Hegel (Yale University), 1948 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - History of Philosophy seminar, 1923 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Introduction to Philosophical Thinking (Yale University: Philosophy 10a, 44b), Circa 1955-1960 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Logic (University of Michigan), Circa 1921-1925 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Logic seminar (University of Michigan), Circa 1921-1925 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Metaphysics, 1945-1961, [ca. (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Problems of Philosophy (Yale University: Philosophy 10b,12b), Circa 1952-1955 (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - Problems of Philosophy (Yale University: Philosophy 10a, 12b), Circa 1957-1961 (Box 53, Folder 17)
    - The Revolt Against Reason in Contemporary Philosophy (Yale University), Circa 1945-1961 (Box 53, Folder 18)
    - Salzburg seminar, 1945-1950 (Box 53, Folder 19)
    - Social Philosophy, 1945-1950 (Box 53, Folder 20)
    - Social Philosophy, 1945-1950 (Box 54, Folder 21)
    - Social Philosophy seminar (Swarthmor), Circa 1925-1945 (Box 54, Folder 22)
    - Theory of Knowledge, [ca. 1945-1961], undated (Box 54, Folder 23-24)
    - Types of Ethical Theory (Yale University): part 1, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 54, Folder 25)
    - Types of Ethical Theory (Yale University): part 2, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 54, Folder 26)
    - Types of Logical Theory (University of Michigan), 1923 (Box 54, Folder 27)
    - Types of Religious Philosophy (University of Minnesota), 1962 (Box 54, Folder 28)
    - What is Philosophy? (Swarthmore College), Circa 1940 (Box 55, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified (University of Michigan), circa 1921-1925, circa 1922-1924 (Box 55, Folder 30-31)
  - Other
    - Analytic Philosophy, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 55, Folder 32)
    - Classical Problems, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 55, Folder 33-34)
    - Concepts of Social Science (Mandelbaum), [ca. 1945-1961] (Box 55, Folder 35)
    - Contemporary Philosophy, 1945, 1947 (Box 55, Folder 36)
    - Contemporary Ethics (Wesleyan University: Philosophy 74), 1962 Spring (Box 55, Folder 37)
    - Ethics, Circa 1925-1945 (Box 55, Folder 38-39)
    - Ethics, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 55, Folder 40-48)
    - Ethics (Philosophy 10b), Circa 1945-1961 (Box 55, Folder 49-51)
    - Ethics (Moral Philosophy), Circa 1945-1961 (Box 56, Folder 52)
    - Exploration, 1927-1928 (Box 56, Folder 53)
    - General Logic (Philosophy 100), Circa 1946-1950 (Box 56, Folder 54-55)
    - History of Modern Philosophy seminar, undated (Box 56, Folder 56)
    - History of Religion, undated (Box 56, Folder 57)
    - Honors Program (Swarthmore), 1925-1939, undated (Box 56, Folder 58)
    - Introduction to Philosophy, Circa 1921-1925 (Box 56, Folder 59)
    - Introduction to Philosophy, Circa 1925-1945 (Box 56, Folder 60-62)
    - Introduction to Religion, Circa 1935-1937 (Box 56, Folder 63)
    - Logic, Circa 1921-1925 (Box 56, Folder 64)
    - Logic, Circa 1925-1945 (Box 56, Folder 65-69)
    - Logic, Circa (Box 56, Folder 70-71)
    - Metaphysics, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 56, Folder 72-75)
    - Moral Philosophy, [ca. (Box 56, Folder 76)
    - Philosophy, Circa 1925-1961 (Box 56, Folder 77)
    - Philosophy 10a, Circa 1956-1961 (Box 56, Folder 78-79)
    - Philosophy 12b, 1955-1958, undated (Box 56, Folder 80)
    - Philosophy 44b, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 56, Folder 81-82)
    - Philosophy of Religion, undated (Box 57, Folder 83-84)
    - Problems of Philosophy (Philosophy 10b), Circa 1953-1954 (Box 57, Folder 85)
    - Problems of Philosophy (Philosophy 12b), Circa 1950s (Box 57, Folder 86)
    - The Revolt Against Reason in Contemporary Thought, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 87)
    - Social Philosophy, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 88-90)
    - Social Theory, undated (Box 57, Folder 91)
    - The Theory of Knowledge, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 92-95)
    - The Theory of Knowledge (Philosophy 44b), Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 96)
    - Types of Ethical Theory, 1931-1932 (Box 57, Folder 97)
    - Types of Ethical Theory, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 98-101)
    - Types of Religious Philosophy (University of Minnesota), 1962 Fall (Box 57, Folder 102)
    - The Ways of Knowing, Circa 1945-1961 (Box 57, Folder 103-104)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 57, Folder 105)
- Personal Papers, 1873-1989; Series IV; 8 linear feet (20 boxes)
  Material in this series is arranged by record type and listed in alphabetical order.
  - Address book, undated (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Audio recordings, 1941 (Box 58, Folder 2)
    See also: box 79-81
  - Certificates, 1893-1983 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    See also: box 7, folder 1
  - Clippings about Blanshard and his work, 1930s-1980s (Box 58, Folder 4-6)
  - Diaries, 1915-1916 (Box 58, Folder 7-8)
  - Diary, 1919
    See: box 63, folder 60
  - Diaries, 1920, 1925 (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1924
    See: box 62, folder 48
  - Diaries, 1926-1930, 1932, 1935-1940s (Box 59, Folder 10-15)
  - Diaries, 1950-1977, 1979-1981 (Box 60, Folder 16-23)
  - Diaries, 1985-1987 (Box 61, Folder 24)
  - Drawings and sketches, 1938-1984 (Box 61, Folder 25)
    See also: box 78, folder 2
  - Family papers
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1888-1919 (Box 61, Folder 26)
      - Memorabilia, 1873-1922, undated (Box 61, Folder 27)
      - Photographs: Blanshard family, 1800s, 1983 (Box 61, Folder 28)
      - Photographs: Blanshard, Brand and Paul, 1892-1972 (Box 61, Folder 29)
      - Photographs: Blanshard, Emily Coulter, 1885-1891, undated (Box 61, Folder 30)
      - Photographs: Blanshard, Francis G., 1880s-1904 (Box 61, Folder 31)
      - Photographs: Blanshard, Roberta Yerkes, 1971-1984 (Box 61, Folder 32)
      - Photographs: Coulter family, 1891-1902, 1985 (Box 61, Folder 33)
      - Photographs: houses and pets, 1900s-1980s (Box 61, Folder 34-35)
    - Blanshard, Frances
      - Address book, undated (Box 62, Folder 36)
      - Certificates, 1946, 1958 (Box 62, Folder 37)
        See also: box 78, folder 3
      - Clippings, 1930s-1960s (Box 62, Folder 38-39)
      - Correspondence, 1900-1949 (Box 62, Folder 40)
        See also: box 13, folder 259 See also: box 14, folder 309-310 See also: box 20, folder 470
      - Correspondence, 1950-1966, undated (Box 62, Folder 41-42)
      - Correspondence: Alumnae Association of Smith College, 1950 (Box 62, Folder 43)
      - Correspondence: Hutchinson, Joanna, 1950-1956 (Box 62, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence: Smith College Club of New Haven, 1956-1960 (Box 62, Folder 45)
      - Diary, 1907-1910, 1912-1913, 1917 (Box 62, Folder 46-48)
      - Diaries, 1926, 1938, 1947-1949, 1951-1957 (Box 63, Folder 49-53)
      - Memorabilia: childhood and student days, 1904-1919 (Box 63, Folder 54)
      - Memorabilia: family, 1909, 1946, undated (Box 63, Folder 55)
      - Memorabilia: Smith College. Class of 1916, 1926-1960 (Box 63, Folder 56)
      - Memorabilia: Swarthmore College, Circa 1939-1945 (Box 63, Folder 57)
      - Memorial tributes, 1966 (Box 63, Folder 58)
      - Notebooks, 1901-1915 (Box 63, Folder 59)
      - Notebook, 1919 (Box 63, Folder 60)
      - Notebooks, undated (Box 64, Folder 61)
      - Photographs, Circa 1900-1966 (Box 64, Folder 62)
      - Research files: Frank Aydelotte of Swarthmore, pre-1966 (Box 64, Folder 63-64)
      - Research files: Portraits of Wordsworth, pre-1959 (Box 65, Folder 65)
      - Research files: Research files: Portraits of Wordsworth: photographs, pre-1959 (Box 65, Folder 66-67)
      - Research files: Portraits of Wordsworth: slides, pre-1959 (Box 65, Folder 68)
      - Research files: Retreat from Likeness in the Theory of Painting, pre-1950 (Box 65, Folder 69)
      - Research files: Women in graduate school at Yale, undated (Box 65, Folder 70)
      - Teaching materials, Circa 1919-1929 (Box 65, Folder 71)
      - Writings
        - General, Circa 1928-1952 (Box 66, Folder 72)
        - General, undated (Box 66, Folder 73-75)
        - Biographical reminiscences, memoirs, 1946-1947, undated (Box 66, Folder 76)
        - Book reviews, 1936-1957 (Box 66, Folder 77)
        - "Confidence in the Future", 1955 (Box 66, Folder 78)
        - Contributions to the Smith College Monthly, 1913, 1915 (Box 66, Folder 79)
        - "Education for Citizenship in the Parochial Schools", "Democracy and the Polish Parochial Schools": drafts and notes, 1918 (Box 66, Folder 80)
        - Essays on status of women, Circa 1919-1920 (Box 66, Folder 81)
        - M.A. thesis: "A Comparison of the Platonic and Aristotelian Theories of Will", 1917 (Box 66, Folder 82)
        - Speeches, Circa 1931-1966, undated (Box 66, Folder 83-84)
        - Student papers, Circa 1913-1916 (Box 66, Folder 85)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 66, Folder 86)
    - Blanshard, Paul
      - Clippings, 1930s-1980 (Box 67, Folder 87-88)
      - Family memorabilia, 1942-1973 (Box 67, Folder 89)
      - Photographs, 1900s, 1970s (Box 67, Folder 90)
        See also: box 61, folder 29
      - Promotion and reviews, 1940s-1970s (Box 67, Folder 91)
      - Writings, 1919-1979 (Box 67, Folder 92-93)
        See also: box 67, folders 87-88
  - Lecture programs, publicity and schedules, 1938-1967 (Box 67, Folder 94)
    See also: box 78, folder 4
  - Medical and legal papers, 1973-1988 (Box 67, Folder 95)
  - Membership cards, identification cards, 1980s, undated (Box 67, Folder 96)
  - Memorabilia
    - Columbia, 1917-1918 (Box 67, Folder 97)
    - England, 1919, 1965 (Box 67, Folder 98)
    - High school, Circa 1909-1910 (Box 67, Folder 99)
    - India, 1915-1917 (Box 67, Folder 100)
    - Oxford, 1913-1919, 1953 (Box 67, Folder 101)
    - Oxford: notebooks, Circa 1913-1920 (Box 68, Folder 102)
    - Oxford: notes, Circa 1913-1920 (Box 68, Folder 103)
    - Oxford: student papers, 1913, circa 1913-1920 (Box 68, Folder 104-105)
    - Peacham, Vermont, undated (Box 68, Folder 106)
    - St. Andrews, 1951-1983 (Box 68, Folder 107)
    - Salzburg, 1953-1954 (Box 68, Folder 108)
    - Swarthmore, 1935, 1938, 1981 (Box 68, Folder 109)
    - United States Army: notebook, 1919 (Box 69, Folder 110)
    - University of Michigan: student notebooks, Circa 1912-1914 (Box 69, Folder 111)
    - University of Michigan: student papers, Circa 1912-1914 (Box 69, Folder 112)
    - University of Michigan: yearbook, 1913 (Box 69, Folder 113)
    - Yale, 1950-1971 (Box 69, Folder 114)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1989, undated (Box 69, Folder 115)
      See also: box 78, folder 5
  - Memorials and obituaries, 1987-1988 (Box 70, Folder 116)
  - Notebooks
    - Analysis, Circa 1954 (Box 70, Folder 117)
    - Art, Circa 1936 (Box 70, Folder 118)
    - Aurelius, Marcus, undated (Box 70, Folder 119)
    - Barth, Brunner, Circa 1961-1962 (Box 70, Folder 120)
    - Behaviorism, Circa (Box 70, Folder 121)
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 70, Folder 122)
    - Bradley, undated (Box 70, Folder 123)
    - Brightman, undated (Box 71, Folder 124)
    - Christian ethics, undated (Box 71, Folder 125)
    - Communism, undated (Box 71, Folder 126)
    - Creed and conduct, undated (Box 71, Folder 127)
    - Education, Circa 1962-1963 (Box 71, Folder 128)
    - Einstein, undated (Box 71, Folder 129)
    - Eliot, undated (Box 71, Folder 130)
    - Faith, undated (Box 71, Folder 131)
    - Freud, Circa (Box 71, Folder 132)
    - Froude, Martineau, undated (Box 71, Folder 133)
    - General, undated (Box 71, Folder 134)
    - Gifford Lectures, undated (Box 71, Folder 135)
    - Good, Circa 1939-1940 (Box 71, Folder 136)
    - Humanism, undated (Box 72, Folder 137)
    - Idealism, Circa 1932 (Box 72, Folder 138)
    - Introduction, undated (Box 72, Folder 139)
    - Jobs, undated (Box 72, Folder 140)
    - Kierkegaard, Circa (Box 72, Folder 141)
    - Luther, Circa 1964-1965 (Box 72, Folder 142)
    - Metaphysics, undated (Box 72, Folder 143)
    - Mill, John Stuart, undated (Box 72, Folder 144)
    - Naturalism, undated (Box 72, Folder 145)
    - Noble Lectures, Circa (Box 72, Folder 146)
    - Peace, undated (Box 72, Folder 147)
    - Philosophy, occasional, Circa 1953-1954 (Box 72, Folder 148)
    - Politics, undated (Box 73, Folder 149)
    - Positivism, undated (Box 73, Folder 150)
    - Prejudice, undated (Box 73, Folder 151)
    - Psychical research, undated (Box 73, Folder 152)
    - Publications, Circa 1947-1985 (Box 73, Folder 153)
    - Rational construction, undated (Box 73, Folder 154)
    - Rational temper, Circa 1951-1952 (Box 73, Folder 155)
    - Reason and religion, Circa 1951-1952 (Box 73, Folder 156)
    - Relations, undated (Box 73, Folder 157)
    - Renan, undated (Box 73, Folder 158)
    - Rome, Circa 1939-1940 (Box 73, Folder 159)
    - Sidgwick, undated (Box 73, Folder 160)
    - Social philosophy, undated (Box 74, Folder 161)
    - Style, undated (Box 74, Folder 162)
    - Tales and limericks, Circa 1964-1965 (Box 74, Folder 163)
    - Teleology, undated (Box 74, Folder 164)
    - Thoughts, 1912 (Box 74, Folder 165)
    - Unidentified, Circa 1932 (Box 74, Folder 166)
    - Unidentified, Circa (Box 75, Folder 167-168)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 75, Folder 169-175)
  - Photograph album: in Europe and Peacham, Vermont, Circa 1940s-1950s (Box 75, Folder 176)
  - Photographs, 1900s (Box 76, Folder 177)
  - Photographs: Germany, India, Mesopotamia, 1914-1917 (Box 76, Folder 178)
  - Photographs, 1918-1919, 1920s, 1930s (Box 76, Folder 179-181)
  - Photographs, 1940s (Box 76, Folder 182)
    See also: box 78, folder 6
  - Photographs, 1950s-1970s (Box 76, Folder 183-185)
  - Photographs: by Melinda Blauvelt, 1971 (Box 76, Folder 186)
  - Photographs: by Karin Keating, 1973 (Box 76, Folder 187)
  - Photographs: by Richard P. Lewis, 1976 (Box 76, Folder 188)
  - Photographs: by David Chalfan, 1977 (Box 76, Folder 189)
  - Photographs, 1980s (Box 76, Folder 190)
  - Photographs: by J. D. Levine, 1980 (Box 76, Folder 191)
  - Photographs: by Kelly Wise, 1980 (Box 76, Folder 192)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 76, Folder 193)
  - Photographs: friends and acquaintances, undated (Box 76, Folder 194)
  - Promotion and reviews for books, 1956, 1973, 1981 (Box 77, Folder 195)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Four Reasonable Men, 1984-1988 (Box 77, Folder 196)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Frank Aydelotte of Swarthmore, 1970-1972 (Box 77, Folder 197)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: The Nature of Thought, 1939-1984 (Box 77, Folder 198)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: On Philosophical Style, 1954-1956, 1970 (Box 77, Folder 199)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Philosophy in American Education, 1945-1946 (Box 77, Folder 200)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: The Philosophy of Brand Blanshard, 1980-1987 (Box 77, Folder 201-202)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Reason and Analysis, 1962-1973 (Box 77, Folder 203)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Reason and Belief, 1975-1982, undated (Box 77, Folder 204)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Reason and Goodness, 1962-1963, undated (Box 77, Folder 205)
  - Promotion and reviews for books: Uses of a Liberal Education, 1974-1984 (Box 77, Folder 206)
  - Verse and games, 1937-1974, undated (Box 77, Folder 207)
  - Vitas and other compiled biographical material, 1950s-1988 (Box 77, Folder 208)
  - Writings about Blanshard and his work, 1967-1970 (Box 77, Folder 209)
    See also: box 58, folder 4-6
  - Writings about Blanshard and his work, 1974, undated (Box 77, Folder 210)
- Oversize, Series V
  - Certificates, 1918-1984 (Box 78, Folder 1)
  - Drawings and sketches, 1945-1953 (Box 78, Folder 2)
  - Family papers
    - Blanshard, Frances: certificates, 1906-1917 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - Lecture programs, publicity, and schedules, undated (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, 1947 (Box 78, Folder 6)
- Audio Tapes, Series VI
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - "The Fringe Benefits of Education," Lake Erie College, 1965 June 14 (Box 79)
    Format: Reel to reel (3 3/4)
  - "Memories and Reflections in Honor of Grace de Laguna," Bryn Mawr, 1979 September 28 (Box 80)
    Format: Audio cassette (60 minute)
  - "The Difficulties of Being Reasonable," New England College, 1981 October 23 (Box 81)
    Format: Audio cassette (C60)